Guide to the Irving S. Olds Collection of Naval and Other Historical Prints and Related Papers 1587-1960 PR 47
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Prints & Related Papers from the Original Olds Donation, 1587-1960, undated; 17.63 Linear feet in 33 flat file folders and 6 boxes
  - Subseries I.A. Prints and Other Documents from the Olds Collection, 1587-1921, undated; 16 Linear feet in flat files and three boxes
    - Print No. 354. Engraving: "A View of his Majesty's Ship Mediator Commanded by the Honble. James Luttrell, ...", 1783 (Folder FF-20)
      Full title: "A View of his Majesty's Ship Mediator Commanded by the Honble. James Luttrell, Attacking Five Sail of the Enemy on the 12th of Decr. 1782, & throwing their Line into Confusion whereby Two of them was Captured; Viz: the Menagere the size of a Sixty Four Gun Ship, Arm'd en Flute; and the Alexander of 28 guns." Painted by Robert Dodd. Engraved by John Peltro. Published London, Septr. 18th 1783 by John Harris Sweetings Alley Cornhill.
    - Print No. 355. Engraving: "This Representation of His Majesty's Ship Mediator of 44 Guns Commanded by the Honourable Capt. James Luttrell. ...", 1784 (Folder FF-20)
      Full title: "This Representation of His Majesty's Ship Mediator of 44 Guns Commanded by the Honourable Capt. James Luttrell. Bearing down at Sunrise, on the Morning of the 12th of December 1782, to Attack Five Sail of the Enemy Mounting in all 130 Guns forming in a Line of Battle to prepare for Action." "This Plate is (by permission) Most humbly Dedicated to His Royal Highness Henry Frederick Duke of Cumberland, Admiral of the White &c. &c. by His Royal Highness's most devoted and most obliged humble Servants, Robert Pollard and Robert Wilkinson." No. 1 Painted by D. Serres Esqr. R.A., and engraved by R. Pollard. "D Serres, 1783" in lower right-hand corner of engraved surface. Published London, January 3, 1784, by R. Pollard and R. Wilkinson. First of a set of three engravings of this privateer action, colored by hand. (Print Nos. 355, 356, 357).
    - Print No. 356. Engraving: "This Representation of His Majesty's Ship Mediator of 44 Guns Commanded by the Honourable Capt. James Luttrell....", 1784 (Folder FF-19)
      Second of set of three engravings of the privateer action (Print Nos. 355, 356, 357). See No. 355 for full title. Published London, June 4, 1784, by R. Wilkinson and R. Pollard. Colored by hand.
    - Print No. 357. Engraving: "This Representation of His Majesty's Ship Mediator of 44 Guns Commanded by the Honourable Capt. James Luttrell. ...", 1784 (Folder FF-19)
      Third of a set of three engravings of the privateer action (Print Nos. 355, 356, 357). See No. 355 for full title. Published London, March 15, 1784, by R. Wilkinson and R. Pollard. Colored by hand.
    - Print No. 357A. Engraving: "This Representation of His Majesty's Ship Mediator of 44 Guns Commanded by the Honourable Capt. James Luttrell. ...", 1784 (Folder FF-19)
      Same print (Print No. 357) in black & white.
    - Print No. 358. Aquatint: "A View of the American Merchant Ship Planter...", 1800 (Folder FF-12)
      Full title: "A View of the American Merchant Ship Planter, beating off a French National Privateer of 22 Guns July 10th 1799. The Ships fought for two Glasses and a half, when the French Privateer sheared off to repair damages, and in one Glass return'd with his Bloody Flag hoisted, with intention to Board, but was repulsed with great Slaughter – The Action lasted five Glasses and a half, when the Privateer was completely Beat off." Inscribed at right under the view: "Planter, Captn. John Watts 18 Guns & 43 Men out of which 4 was Killed & Wounded." Artist and engraver not named. Published London, October 1, 1800, by John Fairburn. Companion to print of the "Constellation" capturing the French frigate "L'Insurgente", published simultaneously by John Fairburn (No. 98).
    - Print No. 359. Aquatint: "The Cambrian of Boston, Willm. Marshall Master, beating off a French Cutter Privateer, on 23 October 1804.", 1805 (Folder FF-12)
      Josh. Cartwright del 1804. Engraved by W. Barnard. Published Boston, February 12, 1805, by C. Cave. This aquatint is unusual in that it was published in America at such an early date and possesses so much quality and charm.
    - Print No. 360. Aquatint: "The Capture of the Gipsey Schooner of New York on the 30th of April 1812, by H.M. Ships Hermes and Belle Poule...", undated (Folder FF-12)
      Full title: "The Capture of the Gipsey Schooner of New York on the 30th of April 1812, by H.M. Ships Hermes and Belle Poule In the Middle of the Atlantic Ocean, after a Chase of three days and nights; she was bound from New York to Bordeaux with a Cargo Value of 50,000 L. The Schooner was a most superb Vessel of 300 Tons burthen carried Ten 18 lb. Carronades and one long 18 pound swivel between her main & foremast with a complement of 80 Men & 2 Ferocious Dogs. She had twice surrender'd to the Hermes previous to falling in with the Belle Poule & endeavoured to effect her escape each time by hauling off on a different tack, while the ship was in the act of taking in sail & rounding to. The crew of the American made a desperate effort to regain possession of their Vessel after being boarded by the boats of the Hermes by 20 Armed Men and the Two Dogs suddenly assailing them, which after a severe struggle were overpowered." Painted by W.J. Huggins, Marine Painter to His Majesty, for Charles Augustus Manning, Esqre., from a design by Captn. Philip Browne, R.N. Commander of H.M.S. Hermes. Engraved by C. Rosenberg. Second state, correcting names of British ships and last line of inscription.
    - Print No. 361. Aquatint: "To Frances Freeling Esqr. Secretary to the General Post Office This Plate representing the situation of H.M. Packet Hinchinbrook...", 1819 (Folder FF-12)
      Full title: "To Frances Freeling Esqr. Secretary to the General Post Office This Plate representing the situation of H.M. Packet Hinchinbrook at the close of an Engagement with the American Privateer, Grand Turk of Salem, on the 1: of May 1814. – The action commenced at 5 hrs: 20 min. P.M. and continued until 7 hrs. 30 min. within pistol shot, during which the Enemy twice laid the Packet abroad but was beaten off; after the failure of the second attempt, the Hinchinbrook obtained a raking position, disabled and obliged the Privateer to sheer off Is very respectfully dedicated by his most obedt. Humble Servt. Willm. James Commr." Statement of the force, armament and losses of each ship below the view at the sides. Drawn by W.I. Pocock. Engraved by Baily. Published February 1, 1819, by Messrs. Colnaghi & Co.
    - Print No. 364. Lithograph: "Combat De La Corvette Anglaise La Vénus contre une frégate Americaine.", undated (Folder FF-12)
      "No. 34" in upper margin. F. Perrot del. Imp. de Lemercier, Benard et Cie.. Published by Victor Delarue, Paris. First state.
    - Print No. 365. Engraving: "A 38 Gun Frigate Bringing too an American schooner.", 1815 (Folder FF-12)
      Drawn by C + L-R.N. Engraved by R. Pollard. Published February 1, 1815, by S. Knight.
    - Olds Catalogue Section J. Miscellaneous Naval Prints (Folder -)
    - Print No. 366. Mezzotint: "Paul Jones shooting a Sailor who had attempted to strike his Colours in an Engagement.", 1779 (Folder FF-12)
      From the Original Picture by John Collet, in the possession of Carington Bowles. Printed for & Sold by Carington Bowles, at his Map & Print Warehouse, No. 69 in St. Paul's Church Yard, London. Published as the Act directs, 2d: Decr. 1779.
    - Print No. 367. Mezzotint: "Capt. Paul Jones shooting a Sailor who had attempted to strike his Colours in an Engagement.", 1780 (Folder FF-15)
      Artist and engraver not named. Colored by hand. Printed for R. Sayer & J. Bennett, Map & Printsellers, London, as the Act directs, January 1, 1780.
    - Print No. 368. Engraving: "Paul Jones the English Corsair shooting his Lieutenant for attempting to strike his Colours.", undated (Folder FF-12)
    - Print No. 370. Handwritten poem of fifty lines, entitled "Paul Jones's Victory.", 1814 (Folder FF-12)
      With drawing of a frigate at top. Signed. "Erastus Gallup Groton 17th January 1814."
    - Print No. 373A. Engraving: "Capture Of The British Frigate Gurriere By The U.S. Frigate Constitution. Vol. 1. page. 334.", undated (Folder FF-12)
      T. Birch A.C.S.A. D. Kimberly Sc. 373A & B (Print and statute) framed together.
    - Print No. 373B. Contemporary official copy of an Act of Congress (Folder FF-12)
      Contemporary official copy of an Act of Congress adopted at the first session of the Fourth Congress of the United States held at Philadelphia and approved on April 20, 1796, by George Washington … authorizing the President of the United States "to continue the construction and equipment, (with all convenient expedition) of two frigates of forty-four and one frigate of thirty-six guns." (Constitution, Constellation & U.S.) 373A & B (print and statute) framed together.
    - Print No. 375. Engraving: "Preparation for War to defend Commerce. The Swedish Chuch Southwark with the building of the Frigate Philadelphia.", 1800 (Folder FF-12)
      Drawn Engraved & Published by W. Birch and Son. Sold by R. Campbell & Co., Philadelphia, 1800. First state.
    - Print No. 376. Water color painting of the U.S. frigate "Philadelphia.", undated (Folder FF-9)
      Artist not known. Initials "AP" on a floating keg at right.
    - Print No. 379. Engraving: "U.S. Frigate Constitution, of 44 Guns.", undated (Folder FF-15)
      Drawn by Wm. Lynn. A Bowen Sc. Published Boston by Wm. Lynn. A scarce early print of "Old Ironsides". Reproduced on cover of "The United States Navy 1776 to 1815", The Grolier Club, New York, 1942 (Irving S. Olds, author).
    - Print No. 381B. Engraving: "La Fregate des Etats-Unis d'Amérique, le President, venant d'appareiller, avec des ris dans les Huniers.", undated (Folder FF-9)
      Another state of No. 381A (not in N-YHS collection), with the same title. Number "13" omitted from upper right-hand corner. Dessine et Grave par Baugean.
    - Print No. 382. Lithograph: "U.S. Frigate Constitution.", undated (Folder FF-19)
      Drawn by William Marsh, Jr. On stone by James Kidder. Senefelder Litho. Co. Portside view of the "Constitution", with mainsails partially furled. First state.
    - Print No. 383. Lithograph: "U.S. Frigate Constitution.", undated (Folder FF-19)
      Drawn by William Marsh, Jr. Pendleton Lith. John Pendleton of Boston introduced lithography into the United States in 1825. Second state of foregoing print. (Print No.382).
    - Print No. 386. Lithograph: "U.S. Frigate Constitution.", undated (Folder FF-9)
      Lithographed and published by J. Baillie, New York. Colored by hand.
    - Print No. 390. Lithograph: "U.S. Frigate Constitution. Malta, Febr. 22nd 1838.", undated (Folder FF-9)
      Painted by J. Evans. On stone by A. Newsam. P.S. Duval, Lith. Philada. U.S. Military Magazine, Army & Navy, Vol. 2nd. Second state of the foregoing lithograph, without part of title reading: "Bearing the Pendant of Come. Jesse Duncan Elliott." Illustration from "U.S. Military Magazine", published by Huddy & Duval, Philadelphia.
    - Print No. 395. Engraving: "An Improved Map of the United States by Shelton & Kensett.", 1813 (Folder FF-19)
      Engraved by A. Doolittle New Haven and T. Kensett Cheshire. At top: "Copy right secured, & entered according to Act of Congress July 6th 1813." Seven small vignettes of naval engagements of the War of 1812. First state. Subsequent states of this map contain nine and ten small vignettes of American naval actions of the War of 1812, respectively. Inhabitants and major produce is listed by state.
    - Print No. 396. Aquatint: "Sprigs of Laurel.", undated (Folder FF-19)
      Drawn and engraved by W. Strickland. Published by John Kneass, Philadelphia. Large view of "Perry's Victory" at top, below which are eight rectangular views of naval engagements or incidents of the War of 1812.
    - Print No. 396. Aquatint: "Sprigs of Laurel"., undated (Box 2)
      Drawn and engraved by W. Strickland. Published by John Kneass, Philadelphia. Large view of "Perry's Victory" at top, below which are eight rectangular views of naval engagements or incidents of the War of 1812. This is a second copy mounted on a board.
    - Print No. 400. French aquatint "Le Fregate A Vapeur Le Fulton, manoeuvrant dans la Rade de New-Yorck…", undated (Folder FF-9)
      Artist and engraver not named. In black and white. Undated. Published by Ostervald l'aíné, Paris.
    - Print No. 402. Engraving: "View of the Wreck of the Steam Frigate Fulton 1st Exploded June 4th 1829.", undated (Folder FF-9)
      From a Sketch by G.W. Teubner. Engraver and publisher not named. Partially colored by hand.
    - Print No. 407. Engraving: "In memory of Commodore Oliver H. Perry, who captured the British Squadron on Lake Erie, Septr. 10th 1813.", 1820 (Folder FF-19)
      On base of monument: "Sacred to the Memory of Commodore Oliver Hazard Perry, of the United States Navy; Who departed this Life August 23rd 1819, Aged 34 Years." Drawn by E.C. Brenton. Engraved by W.H. Bassett & A. Willard. Copyrighted, February 5, 1820.
    - Print No. 409. Aquatint: "Action of Quallah Battoo...", undated (Folder FF-9)
      Full title: "Action of Quallah Battoo, As Seen From The Potomac At Anchor In The Offing; J. Downes Esq. Commander. Feb. 5 1832." Aquatinted by G.G. Smith, Boston. Colored by hand.
    - Print No. 410. Lithograph: "This View of the Opening of the Dry Dock U.S. Navy Yard Gosport...", undated (Folder FF-9)
      Full title: "This View of the Opening of the Dry Dock U.S. Navy Yard Gosport, is Very Respectfully Dedicated to Loammi Baldwin Esq. By his very Obedient Servant, Joseph Goldsborough Bruff." "Delaware" entering the dry dock. Drawn on Stone by G. Lehman from a Sketch by J.G. Bruff. Childs & Inman's Lith. Philadelphia. One of a pair of lithographs, the other also depicting the U.S.S. "Delaware", but inside of the dry dock.
    - Print No. 413. French lithograph: "Vaisseau À Deux Ponts Américain. Scènes Maritimes.", undated (Folder FF-9)
      Cassé frères, à St. Gaudens. Gadola à Lyon – (Déposé) View of an American frigate pursuing and firing on a three-masted vessel of Tripolitan rig.
    - Print No. 414. French lithograph: "Frègate Des États-Unis dématée de son mat de misaine", undated (Folder FF-9)
      F. Perrot del. "No. 36" in margin. Paris, L. Turgis, Jne. View of a naval action between four frigates. The foremast of an American frigate falls in a close engagement with a French ship, shown in the foreground. Another state of this print with the same title was published by Victor Delarue et Cie, Paris. (No. 662, not in N-YHS collection)
    - Print No. 415. Aquatint: "A View of An Homeward-Bound American Ship taking her departure from the Lands End.", 1797 (Folder FF-9)
      Designed & Engraved by W. Elmes. Published March 6, 1797, by John Fairburn 146 Minories London.
    - Print No. 416. Lithograph: "The American Tar. 'Do'nt Give Up The Ship'.", 1845 (Folder FF-9)
      Lithographed and published by N. Currier, New York, 1845.
    - Print No. 417. Lithograph: "Harry Bluff.", undated (Folder FF-9)
      Below the title is a "Sea Song" as follows: In battle he fell, when in Victory crown'd, The Flag shot away, fell in atters around__ The foe thought he'd struck, when he cried out _ Avast! And the colors of Columbia he nail'd to the mast, And he died like a true Yankee Sailor.
      Lith. & Pub. by N. Currier, 152 Nassau St. N.Y.
    - Print No. 418. Engraving: "America. Amerique.", 1791 (Folder FF-9)
      Ap. Theodorum Viero Venetiis cum Prvil. Ecc. Sen. Anno 1791.
    - Print No. 422. U.S. Ship Stamps., undated (Folder FF-15)
      Set of twenty-four mint Commemorative United States Postage Stamps concerning ships, mounted in a decorative hand-colored panel, entitled "U.S. Ship Stamps", inscribed in a box under a drawing of a frigate.
    - Print No. 423. Lithograph: "Oct. 15. 1805. – Brig Blown Up by Fulton's Torpedo and her annihilation complete", undated (Folder FF-14)
      Designed by Fulton. L.N. Rosenthal's lith. Philada.
    - Print No. 424. Aquatint: "This representation of His Majesty's Ship Majestic, 57 Guns, John Hayes, Esq. Captain, ...", undated (Folder FF-19)
      Full title: "This representation of His Majesty's Ship Majestic, 57 Guns, John Hayes, Esq. Captain, meeting with Two French Frigates, an American Private Ship of War, a Spanish Lima Ship, -& a Brig on the 3rd of Feby. 1814, in Latde.. 37. N. and Longde.. 20. W. – and Capturing one of the Frigates: - Is by Gracious Permission, dedicated to His Most Excellent Majesty William IVth by His Majesty's Faithful Subject & Servant, John Hayes, Capt. R.N. C. B." Painted by Gilbert. Engd. By C. Hunt. (Ackermann & Co Exect)
    - Print No. 425. Aquatint: "Defeat of the British Army, ...", undated (Folder FF-19)
      Full title: "Defeat of the British Army, 12,000 strong, under the Command of Sir Edward Packenham, in the attack of the American Lines defended by 3,600 Militia, commanded by Major General Andrew Jackson, January 8the 1815, on Chalmette plain, five miles below New Orleans, on the left bank of the Mississipi." (At the left) "Drawn on the Field of Battle, and painted by Hthe Laclotte, archt and assist. Engineer in the Louisiana Army. the Year 1815." At the right is a similar title and inscription in French. Desine par Hche. Laclotte. Grave par P.L. Debucourt.
    - Print No. 426. Aquatint: "Battle Of New Orleans And Defeat of the British under the Command of Sir Edward Packenham. By Genl. Andrew Jackson 8th. Jany. 1815.", undated (Folder FF-5)
      At left: "American force 6700 Militia. 7 Killed 6 Wounded." At right: "British force 14000 Regulars. Killed and Wounded 2600." Drawn by S. Seymour. Engraved by J.W. Steel. Published by Wm. H. Morgan No. 114 Chestnut St. Philadelphia.
    - Olds Catalogue Section K. Caricatures of War of 1812 (Folder -)
    - Print No. 429. Etching: Caricature by William Charles, entitled: "A Wasp taking a Frolick Or a Sting for Johnny Bull.", undated (Folder FF-14)
      Wm Charles Del et Sculp. Standing figure of John Bull, sword in right hand, stung through his middle by the tail of a wasp, with poem below.
    - Print No. 430. Etching: Caricature by William Charles, entitled: "Johnny Bull in a Fret...", undated (Folder FF-14)
      Full title: "Johnny Bull in a Fret Oh these Wasps & Hornets! the dreadful little Insects, how they Sting! Oh woe is me! why did I disturb Their Nest!!" Pubd. at 72 Chestnut St Phila. Standing, stamping figure of John Bull, pursued by seven wasps and hornets.
    - Print No. 433.. Engraving: "The Shannon commanded by Capt, Broke...", 1813 (Folder FF-14)
      Full title: "The Shannon commanded by Capt. Broke engageing and capturing the Chesapeake american Frigate, Capt, Lawrence. in sight of Boston June 1st 1813 this gallant action was terminated in 15 mins capt Broke boarding at the head of a body of his crew. the american mounted 24 pounders (the Shannon but 18) is 140 tons larger, and contained 110 more men than the British. capt. Lawrence died of his wounds soon after she struck – a Subject we hope Mr Maddison will not forget to mention the next meeting of Congress." Caricature. Artist and engraver not named. Pubd. July 1813 by S. Knight No 3 Sweetings Alley RE
    - Print No. 434. Engraving: "British Valour and Yankee Boasting or, Shannon versus Chesapeake.", 1813 (Folder FF-14)
      G. Cruikshank fect. Pubd September 1st 1813 for the Proprietor of Town Talk – Caricature, depicting the boarding of the Chesapeake by the crew of the Shannon.
    - Olds Catalogue Section L. Portraits of Naval Commanders (Folder -)
    - Print No. 437. Lithograph: "Com. William Bainbridge. of the U.S. Navy. Born 1774 – Died 1833 – Aged 59.", undated (Folder FF-14)
      J.W. Jarvis, pinxt. Litho. of Endicott. Litho. and Published by G. Endicott, 359, Broadway, N.Y.
    - Print No. 438A. Two portraits framed together: (A) Engraving: "Commodore Bainbridge Captur'd and destroyd the Java"., undated (Folder FF-14)
      G. Delleker Sc. Published by J. Kneass 125 Market St Phila. Ribbon in tribute below portrait reads, "Avast! Boys She's Struck!"
    - Print No. 438B. Two portraits framed together: (B) Aquatint: "Captain I. Hull Eluded the British Fleet July 1812 – Captured the Guerriere Aug. 1812.", undated (Folder FF-14)
      Aquatinted by W. Strickland. Published by John Kneass Phila. Ribbon in tribute below portrait reads, "First in Victory First in Battle."
    - Print No. 441. Engraving: "Commodore John Barry"., undated (Folder FF-14)
      Stuart pinx. Edwin sc. Illustration from "The Port Folio", July 1813.
    - Print No. 443. Engraving: "Commodore Chauncey of Lake Ontario"., undated (Folder FF-14)
      Pub. by P. Price Jr. Philada. First state, with name of publisher. Ribbon in tribute under portrait reads, "Hero of Lake Ontario".
    - Print No. 444. Portrait and letter framed together: (a) Engraving: "Commodore Chauncey". (b) Autograph letter, dated June 10, 1834. (Folder FF-14)
      Artist, engraver and publisher not named. Cut out copy of print, omitting "of Lake Ontario" from the title. Second state, omitting "Pub. by P. Price Jr. Philada." Autographed letter reads, "High esteem for the Father and warm wishes for the happiness of the fair daughter are cherished by I. Chauncey".
    - Print No. 446. Lithograph: Reproduction of the rare copper-plate engraving of Commodore Stephen Decatur, engraved by J.O. Lewis after a drawing by G. Strickland., undated (Folder FF-14)
      A reduced facsimile of the original of this print appears as the frontispiece of "American Engravers upon Copper and Steel" by Mantle Fielding, Philadelphia 1917 (No. 713, not in N-YHS collection).
    - Print No. 447. Engraving: [Stephen Decatur] No title., undated (Folder FF-14)
      Drawn & engrd. by St. Memin Philadelphia.
    - Print No. 448A. Portrait and letter framed together: (A) Lithograph: "Commodore J.D. Elliott.", undated (Folder FF-14)
      J.W. Orr N.Y.
    - Print No. 448B.. Portrait and letter framed together: (B) Autograph letter., 1828 (Folder FF-14)
      Dated Carlisle, April 22, 1828, addressed by J.D. Elliott to Hon. Saml. L. Southard, Secretary of the Navy.
    - Print No. 449. Mezzotint: "Commodore Hopkins, Commander in Chief of the American Fleet.", 1776 (Folder FF-14)
      Publish'd as the Act directs 22, Augt. 1776. by Thos. Hart London. First state, including "London" in publication data.
    - Print No. 450. Mezzotint: "Commodore Hopkins, Commander in Chief of the American Fleet.", 1776 (Folder FF-14)
      Publish'd as the Act directs 22 Augt. 1776 by Thos. Hart. Second state, omitting "London" from publication data.
    - Print No. 451. Mezzotint: "Commodore Hopkins, Commander in Chief of the American Fleet.", 1776 (Folder FF-15)
      Ioh. Martin Will excudit Aug. Vend. Publish'd as the Act directs 22. Augt. 1776 by Thos. Hart London.
    - Print No. 452. Mezzotint: "Admiral Hopkins Commandeur en Chef, de la Flotte Americaine des XIII. Provinces unies.", undated (Folder FF-14)
      Peint par Wilckenson a Boston. Se vend a Londres chez. Thom. Hart. Second state, with spelling of "Commendeur" corrected.
    - Print No. 454. Mezzotint: "This Portrait of Captn. Isaac Hull, of the United States Navy...", 1813 (Folder FF-14)